the um the suta today it's uh angut 321
it's called purity
and uh it's a short suta but quite
interesting useful as well so it starts
by [clears throat] the Buddha addressing
the bikus saying the these there are
these three kinds of purity what three
purity of body purity of speech and
purity of thought
what is purity Purity of body. It is
when a biku abstains from killing living
creatures, stealing and inselibacy. That
is called purity of body.
What is purity of speech? It is when a
biku abstains from false, malicious,
harsh and trivial speech. This is called
purity of speech.
And what is uh purity of thought? It is
when a biku when there is a sensual
desire internally understands there is a
central desire internally for me. When
there is no sensual desire internally he
understands there is no central desire
internally for me. He understands how
unarisen sensual desire arises and how
arisen sensual desire is abandoned and
how abandoned sensual desire does not
arise again in the future.
So when there is ill will internally, he
understands there is ill will internally
for me. When there is no ill will
internally, he understands there is no
ill will internally for me. He
understands how unaren ill will arises
and how ill will is abandoned and how
abandoned ill will does not arise again.
When there is indolence and lethargy
internally, he understands there is
indol indolence and lethargy internally
for me. When there is no indolence and
lethargy internally, he understands
there is no indolent in indolence and
lethargy internally. For me, he
understands how unreasony arises and how
a risen one is abandoned and how
abandoned one does not arise in the
future. Um the fourth hindrance uh when there is
Um the fourth hindrance uh when there is
restlessness and anxiety internally,
he understands there is restlessness and
anxiety internally for me. When there is
no restlessness and anxiety, he
understands that there is no
restlessness anxiety. And he understands
how unarrison arises and how arisen is
abandoned and how abandoned does not
arise in the future.
I forgot to do this part.
So when there is doubt internally, he
understands there is doubt internally
for me. When there is no doubt
internally, he understands there is no
doubt internally for me. He understands
how unreason arises and how reason doubt
is abandoned and how abandoned doubt
does not arise again in the future. That
is called purity of thought. And then
the Buddha finished with a verses saying
these are these um there are these three
kinds of purity. Purity of body, purity
of speech and purity of thought. One who
is clean and down with purity has washed
off all evil. they say.
So yeah, as we can see obviously
the suit addresses the the three fields
of action,
action by body, by speech and thought.
So purity of body self-explanatory, the
precepts, the virtue that's obviously
summed up in the in the three major ones
which is killing, stealing and insibacy.
Then it includes uh the domain of speech
which is um anything from false speech,
malicious, harsh, pointless, trivial,
useless. That's avoiding those things.
It's how one purifies his speech. And
then the puritive thought in this suta
was um
expressed through basically
understanding full understanding of the
five hindrances.
So understanding of central desire,
understanding the mind affected with
central desire when the mind is affected
with central desire, understanding the
mind unaffected by central desire when
the mind is not affected by it,
understanding how it arises,
understanding how it's abandoned and
understanding how it doesn't arise. So
and then the same goes for real will,
indolence and lethargy, restlessness and
anxiety and then um doubt as well.
and then um doubt as well.
So the interesting thing and I think
venerable mentioned that in on our
suta website is to note that how the
suta does not define purity by the
absence of the five hindrances.
It defines it by knowing that they are
present when they are present and
knowing that they are absent when they
are absent. So that is the purity of
thought. Not purity of thought is not
not having the mind affected with
sensuality. Purity of thought is basically knowing
Purity of thought is basically knowing
the mind affected with sensuality as
mind affected with sensuality. Mind
affected with without real will as mind
affected with those things.
So
it's like um
the point is obviously that presence of
those things the hindrances presence of
sensuality ill will um sloth and torpo
restlessness and anxiety and doubt
they're not um in and of themselves they
are not hindrances.
It's when they're present in the mind.
When that is not known, that is how one
is hindered.
When it's known, one is unhindered
pretty much by the same thing. There was
that other I think we might have done it
even during these um during these
sessions where um where he states
exactly the same. says that there are
things they're like signs of beauty
that that come and mind picks up on them
and it's like that in and of itself does
not constitute a hindrance but it's when
the mind or rather when you attend
wrongly through to that experience of
mind affected or mind seeing a sign of
beauty attending wrongly
is how
you become hindered by it. It's how that
um sensuality becomes something you're
affected and then say there's a there is
a sign of of ugly sign of kind of
aversion which in and of itself again
does not constitute a hindrance.
Attending to it wrongly you are
hindered. In other words, not seeing the
mind, not seeing the wild animal to the
sufficient extent as something that's
recipient or something that's um say
under the pressure of sign of beauty or
sign of aversion. That's how you become
hindered. And then he went he went to to
explain the same for these other five
hindrances saying pretty much uh like
being lazy, acting lazily after the meal
and so on is how you become hindered by
indolence and lethargy. wrongly
attending to that um restances and
anxiety and then was it the doubt? Yeah,
the doubt says there are things that are
that lend themselves to doubt but again
still does not do not constitute a
hindrance of doubt. Only wrongly
attending to the mind that's under the
pressure of things that are ambiguous in
the nature is how you fall into the
hindrance of doubt. So learning how to
attend rightly does not remove the whole
picture. Does not prevent the sign of
beauty or sign of ugly or things
suitable to doubt or lack of energy but
it prevents you uh falling into the the
the framework of of that hindrance.
Basically it prevents you being trapped
by it.
So that's that's what pointed out
said there are hindrances when there is
craving and without ignorance craving
cannot exist which means basically if
you are rightly attending or seeing the
mind clearly to the right extent as
something that's under the pressure of
say sign of beauty uh you won't be
affected amidst those things. So you are
unhindered amidst the world of hindrances pretty
amidst the world of hindrances pretty
much.
So, and that's he gave a he gave an
analogy in his notes saying it's like a
if someone has the key for a cell door
and knows for a fact they can get out at
will whenever they want.
Can you really call that an
imprisonment? So, if nobody else knows
about a key, only you, only you have it,
even people that think you are trapped
in
don't know about it and you could at
will just open the door and leave. Would
it be correct to say you are the one who
is imprisoned? No. And that's the point.
So um
yeah so the suit is short but I did kind
of extrapolate a few practical questions
um on the basis of it as in obviously
you know we speak about purity of body
purity of virtue often so we're not
going to dwell on that too much. um you
can listen to the previous talks for
that. Uh but purity of speech and then
obviously purity of thought is is the
most uh um refined and it's not just
about say avoiding thinking about
certain things and so on but it's it's
measured by the clarity of the
understanding of the animal of the
cheetah. So to what extent say when when the
So to what extent say when when the
sensual sensuality arises or real will
to what extent do you regard that
experience as a whole
as mind affected with ill will that I'm
experiencing or
or
I'm affected by um affected by ill will
through basically experiencing um this
or that that upset me in the world and
mind is not even seen in that equation.
So how much of it do you see like it's
between you and the mind or how much of
it do you see oh it's between me and
whatever circumstance in the world made
me upset or made me uh lustful or made
me doubtful cuz that's the point you
begin by not seeing the mind at all. So
it's it's it's it's all there in the
world. It's all on the level of sense
objects and so on
through containers through containers of
virtue purifying your speech right choices and
purifying your speech right choices and
everything else we often talk about you
are as I said many times before creating
some a degree of some space in between
where you could actually start to notice
your mind as a thing in between there.
So you might initially like oh this
upset me or that made me um full of
desire but before that or rather between
you and what you're seeing there is that
animal sitting there affected by that
thing and that's what needs to be seen
because fundamentally that's really the
root of the problem. That's why you
practice restraint. That's why you you
you you um you uh pay attention to the
choice of your actions
because all of that feeds that animal
that's initially invisible to you, that
mind. So the purity of thought is measured and
So the purity of thought is measured and
trained through noticing
that state of the animal, not trying to
get rid of it, not trying to change it,
just containing it. When I say do things
on the right level, it really just means
contain them to the right extent.
Because if you're too preoccupied of
trying to resolve something
instantaneously, well, you don't want to
be containing it.
You're afraid that it might spill out
and so on, which means okay, you haven't
developed the container sufficiently
enough. And and that's why it's it's just it's
And and that's why it's it's just it's
not even like there is there's no other
way really like you can't you can't
bypass this. The only way to understand
the mind to the full extent as something
affected by a hindrance and therefore
you become unaffected by it is to
contain it to the extent necessary to
endure it to the extent necessary until
that container is developed sufficiently
enough. There is no other way. So how
much of that endurance and container
uh will whether it's going to be
unpleasant or not so unpleasant depends
on how much you're really resisting the
idea of it or not so um
go back to this one.
So then the um the the questions for
reflection uh that I this I said is I
extrapolated. So like for example and
again these things can be you know where
if you say okay I don't see my mind
therefore the suta doesn't apply to me.
Yeah fundamentally sure you need to see
your mind for this to make any sense but
that doesn't mean you shouldn't be
trying [clears throat] as I said there
before. So So
meditation, samadi,
any form of say composure should be
revolving and be preoccupied really with learning
and be preoccupied really with learning
how to contain that mind. How to not
throughara
you yourself spill out and blame the
world. Blame the circumstances. Blame
the sign of beauty. Blame the sign of
ugly. blame things suitable that lend
themselves to doubt easily as that which
is doubt as that which is ill will. So
that's what Samad is. It's not about
removing the whole picture and not
experiencing any of those disturbing
things. It's about training in their
containment. So
So
any form of meditation should really be
a informed reflection to call it that
way. So you can ask yourself like in
regard to this sut in particular you
could you could ask yourself so okay how
like my recent actions
today two days ago I don't know last
week as far as I can recently remember
uh how often were they driven by desire
carelessness and ill will and that
already implies how often did I look
past the state of mind and acted towards
the world for pleasure, avoiding pain,
resolving doubt, which implicitly
obviously assumes that that's where the
problem was. And even if I theoretically
learned that that's not where the
problem was, how often did I give in to
my still ingrained habit of still acting
out towards the domain of the world
through body, speech, and mind even if
even despite theoretically knowing that
that's not where I should be looking for
solution. So, how often did I allow
myself to act out?
And then obviously if you So, okay, I
could have done better, maybe I did
good, maybe I didn't. The point is,
okay, it's not going to be perfect, but
the point is to start to recognize,
okay, how many times I didn't.
So, how many times I actually didn't act
out despite the pressure?
Because that's what this why this sut is
important because it tells you see
that's already a level of purity.
Because again the initial view and
attitude by most people would be
complete absence of these hindrances is
what purity is. Therefore they fall into
these self-hypnotic meditation
techniques not incidentally because
that's the st that's the that's the
layer when you are unaware of pretty
much everything.
So you feel like this is the purest
because there is nothing there. Well,
there's a lot there obviously it's just
that you're not noticing it. But the
point is the purity is not measured by
the absence. The purity is measured by
your clarity in regard to whatever's
present disturbing five disturbing
domain five disturbing things.
So you ask yourself how often did I act
out this many times or that in this instance
this many times or that in this instance
or that instance? How often I didn't?
How often did I restrain myself? And the
point is, as I said, to rewrite that
expectation that the absence of those
things altogether is the the the
benchmark. It isn't. But to start to
develop the clarity in regard to the
difference as well, the difference
between well, how was it when I acted
out, when I gave in to my old
assumptions, and how did it feel when I
didn't? What's the difference between
the two? So what's the difference
between an enduring pressure to act out
and then act out and enduring pressure
to act out and not act not acting out?
Because the reason people choose acting
out um perpetually repeatedly is because
not acting out at the time feels like oh
unbearable. I have to act out. I just
have to act out. I'll deal with it
later. I have to act out. But the more
familiar you become with it, even in
like through this kind of retroactive
uh contemplation of h how did it feel
when I actually restrained myself? How
did it feel when I didn't? What was the
difference? Uh even that can be
gradually uh familiarizing you with it
and you actually get to understand and
kind of develop a broader view that well
it wasn't that bad. it feels that bad at
the moment, but from a from a from a
bigger from a point of view of a bigger
picture. I actually contained it and it wasn't
I actually contained it and it wasn't
too bad. So next time you can remind you
well you would be automatically reminded
of that if you frequently recollect
those things. Next time when it feels
like oh I can't bear this I have to act
out and it's like but I already I I I
borrow it in the past. It wasn't
it it wasn't end of the world for sure.
So why don't I do it again?
And it kind of reinforcing
that reminding yourself and as I said
trying to discern the difference even if
it's like a vague oh it felt like this
felt like that. You don't need to be
like like you know super psychologically
accurate or something. It's more like
just being familiar with the other side
of things such as pressure came up and I
didn't act.
First you learn to not again not
overshoot the mark which is pressure
came up I didn't act but I feel like I
must still get rid of the pressure
because that's where the purity is. Well
it's it's not. You learn that it isn't.
The purity is simply maintaining the
clear picture regardless of what state
of the wild the animal is. So the animal
can be kicking, screaming, trying to
bite you realize that's fine as long as
I don't give into this and don't act out
of it.
Um it will have to calm down basically
that's what you understand and that's
where that patient the the count
patience aspect comes from. Um so then
like the the another say retroactive
reflection that you can do would be in
regard to the speech. So it's the same
principle obviously but now you're
refining it. You know you can say yeah I
didn't act I wanted really to to do this
act out my body but I didn't. However,
you know I did say something
uh it wasn't too bad but it could have
been better. So now you are addressing
that that domain the domain of speech
and again you can do that as a daily
practice uh not out of some sort of neurosis
uh not out of some sort of neurosis
trying to find out the answers they will
then magically make the whole thing fall
into place but it's more like no no I'm
going through the motions of actively
reminding myself of what I chose to do
and what I didn't whether I chose
restraint or giving in.
whether I spoke out of greed, out of
aversion, out of irritation, out of
hindrance or I didn't.
It's not about learning something new in
that sense. Like as I said, digging up
for new revelations, information. It's
about just reminding the mind
of what it already knows, but it kind of
tends to look past it.
So, it's not these reflections.
Basically if you're doing them for that
purpose uh it might take some time as I
said to get used to it but if you're
doing it for that purpose
just this type of questioning it's
already a forming a type of samadei it's
already containing your mind rightly
it's already increasing however you know
uh whatever like to whatever minuscule
degree it's already but it's still
increasing a a a a some degree of
clarity in regard to the whole >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> So [clears throat]
recollect again about your recent speech
about today about yesterday and you say
oh I said something I shouldn't have
again you realize okay now it's not
about resolving that
making grand determinations I'll never
do this and I'll never do that and I'll
never go there again because like it's
like all of that secondary it's about
familiarizing yourself with a state of
mind which your current experience that
has recollected the fact that mind got
the better of you made you act how does
it feel now when you shed light to that
it's going to feel unpleasant and that's
the point
sure you might have a tendency oh I'm
worthless and I'll let no now that's
going too far now question that now
because it's about familiarization
Whether it's affecting the mind
pleasantly, unpleasantly, that's not the
point. And that's the trap you should
try and not fall into.
Be concerned about how it feels.
Either way, you're containing it and then
and then
extend the same reflection further in a
sense of like u okay
I did well or I didn't do well. Either
way, this is how it feels. this is how
the difference feels. Let me remind
myself of the values I should try and
then um persist through u tomorrow and
next day and day after. If the speech is
beneficial, timely, necessary, if I'm
unsure about it, well then I'll probably
just veer on the side of restraint. But
either way, remind yourself about
choosing to speak basically. And when
the pressure to say something builds up,
again, you don't have to just every
single time say no to it, but you need
to have perspective in regard to it,
regardless of how it feels.
So that kind of brings brings me to the
to the third point that you can you can
be asking yourself and thinking about
which is so do you clearly or how
clearly do you recognize the context
behind any currently enduring pressure any
any currently enduring pressure any
hindrance while it is present. In other
words, when you are acutely pressured to
act out
towards sensuality or out of ill will
and so on, how much of the context do
you still retain or are able to retain?
Is it like none? you only see it
afterwards or you are able to to to keep
some perspective because obviously
that's that's kind of something that
should be again revisited, recollected,
reminded and developed. And how do you
develop that context? Well, exactly how
I just described the first two
reflections. That's how you develop it.
That's how through this frequent um
reminding of what's skillful, what's
unskillful, the difference uh the
difference between acting out, the
difference between not acting out and
staying with the pressure, that is how
you are, as I said informing that
context. And and the clearer you become
um
regarding that that that experience as a
whole, then the the acuteness of the
hindrance will be diminished to that extent. In
will be diminished to that extent. In
other words, hindrance can be like
really over like almost overwhelming
you, but the context remains to not act
out that it's the state of the mind that
needs to be contained, not be projected
onto the world towards the sense objects
and then fall into a trap. So through
that gradual as I said broadening of
that context is how you eventually will
stop acting out you know like obviously
you abandon course acting out but these
these uh finer ways in terms of like the
speech and so on where even your
intention might be ambiguous and stuff
well that's how you get to approoted
like you can't necessarily pinpoint um
as easily as these coarse forms of
actions and you don't have to because if
the context becomes imperturbable able
enough that endurance is the way out,
not acting out as the way out. Anything
within that will have to will have to
eventually completely be eradicated. So,
so then um yeah another thing you can be
asking yourself following the same line
of the five hindrances is um say when
you're not acutely pressured do you
recognize certain say environmental
triggers conditions that would act as precursor
conditions that would act as precursor
to a hindrance precursor to a pressure
as I said obviously they're going to be
the obvious ones which presumably you
would have been avoiding
well beforehand, but even the subtler
ones. In other words, can you foresee
In other words, can you foresee
where certain experiences, signs and
features of those experiences are
leading to before it's too late, before
the pressure is too much and you can't
stop now? Because that's that's
obviously important. That's like that's
the the the the value of like learning
things beforehand because
um if you don't start uh anticipating
where a certain set of choices, actions
and so on is taking you well there will
be no mind development for you really
and that's that simile of the cook that
the Buddha talked about.
Um and then the last one which yeah it's
it's kind of useful and um ties in what
I already said which is can you um can
you recall
uh an instance when a hindrance
actually ceased on its own like
completely. So you didn't act out
So you didn't act out
you endured it. you contained it and
then next thing you know it's it was
gone. So again it's not because you're
So again it's not because you're
expecting to learn something new from it
but it's in order to recollect it in
order to bring it back
because there will be subtler aspects of
that that mind is simply overlooking. So
it's to become more and more familiar
with how did that feel
because see whenever there is an acute
hindrance pressuring you to act out
towards desire towards this towards that
staying with the pressure feels like
there it has no end. So you you can say
no to your desire once or twice but the
pressure is still there. The pressure is
still there and basically the mind fall
well you fall into this view
uh there and then that well if you don't
act out this will be um uh kind of
trapping you and closing you this
pressure forever although you know like
and you can tell to yourself no of
course nothing lasts forever I know it
will stop doesn't matter the mind
doesn't listen to that. So you you you
you're telling to yourself, "Oh,
everything will pass away and
impermanence." But the mind doesn't
understand that, doesn't hear it. Why is
that? Well, as I said many times before,
because he doesn't speak your language.
Um the practical reason for the mind not
really taking any heed of the fact that
yes, the pressure will have to cease and
you know it, yet the mind still acts
like it will never cease. It's because
well, you haven't been reflecting on it
long enough. like you haven't been going
through the repetition of those
recollections sufficiently enough for it
to sink in for it for the mind to really
become convinced oh yeah yeah of course
yeah no it will cease
so that's why you should be also yeah
recollect the hindrance recollect the
hind uh the triggers and so on but also
recollect the times when actually you
didn't act out and the hindrance
subsided on its own the pressure was
gone you didn't act out you didn't do
anything on account of and it was gone.
How did that feel?
Again, ask the question, don't
necessarily seek the answer because
asking the question
reveals the mind or leaves the mind with
it, so to speak. And the mind will
remember how it felt. The the animal
will remember how it felt. That's really
what what what you who whom you're
asking for. You're not asking for
yourself. How did it feel? Well, it felt
like this. It's irrelevant. How did it
feel? and feel how it felt. Get the
animal to feel it how it felt.
So next time the acute pressure is there
trying to overwhelm you. Again you might
ask the question but you might not even
have to ask the question because that is
the exact instance that you've been
recalling recollecting. So the mind will
now be reminded of what you reminded it
beforehand, which is how it felt when
the thing ceased, which means, oh, it
will cease and now the animal got it.
Sure, it can forget again. That's why
it's not like you do it once and you're
done. But the point is to to to to get
the animal to feel the difference
because it knows the difference. You
like even even if somebody made zero
effort in practice simply by by going
through experiences on a daily basis
there must have been an instance where
there was an acute sensuality or ill
will and for one reason or the other
knowing nothing of the dhamma for
whatever reason was not able to act out
was just left with that pentup pressure
couldn't act out couldn't do anything
about it [snorts]
and it disappeared it's just that you
know again if if he's completely
uninstructed he will not know to
recollect that the difference and start
start highlighting the difference. He'll
just look past it and move on and
continue acting towards objects in the
world as if they were the problem.
But now you know better. So you want to
recollect how it felt
to develop a context that will
regardless of how powerful the the
pressure might be
seizes seizes immediately like uh
instant or simultaneously se recognizes
that it's end
it's end
it recognizes that doesn't matter how
long this lasts
how cute it might get I remember how it
ends because every hindrance ends the same
because every hindrance ends the same
through that feeling of it's gone,
relieved, unhindered, no weight.
So that will be sufficient
to remind the animal to not panic, not
feel as enclosed and entrapped as it
otherwise would.
And that's why that's important. So
that's why these reflections are the
true meditations really because you're
asking these questions not for the sake
of as I said intellectual reasoning or
finding some like psychological answers
but just to bring shed the light and set
up the context that are then left with
the mind. So you can ask a question and
then sit with it and if the mind wanders
away come back reask it or ask a
different question in regard to similar.
The questioning part is what keeps you
actively engaged so you don't fall into
the mindless mantra recitation or or
sensation watching method. But you're
not asking for the sake of answers
really. So the questioning part is what
engages you but then you stop halfway
through for the mind to feel to discern
answers for the answers to sink down to
the mind. not not like not for the sake
of your theory.
So so that's pretty much how you train
in regard to purifying your thoughts,
broadening the context on the basis of
not acting out of hindrances, not trying
to get rid of the pressure, containing
it and finding the stable
[clears throat] untouched ground within
that. That's pretty much it.